hi Angelie how are you doing I'm doing
good sanay how are you I'm really good
thank you do you have a very chill
relaxed weekend or is it busy it is
pretty chill and I'm having a great time
because I'm going to be having a
conversation with
you so that's sweet of you say and
perfect um I'm really happy to H be
having this conversation as well because
I think you're going to bring in a very
different perspective to the
conversation and will be different from
all the conversations I've had till now
it's your your experience with building
teams and scaling so I'm definitely
looking forward to this and I'm I'm
really excited to know about your
journey throughout this starting from
planning your journey so considering
that you worked at lollipop ter logic
now at ICC alumar so have you always
been planning your career or how has the
journey been so far okay so Sanjay the
short answer is no I did not plan where
I would Lear to be after 10 years 20
years in my career but it's kind of like
figuring out your journey is quite
inevitable I would say so yeah I have a
background of science graduation I a
science graduate with computers as well
and then landed into design started
exploring my way through design and of
course that was something that I knew
this is where I would land better so
that was decided that I mean I kind of
figured out that design will give me the
kind of exposure which I am also seeking
which will keep me happy along the way
but honestly I thought let's figure out
the way that's been my Approach always
in life let's see how it comes so be
open to change kind of so it is like I
did not decide but yes certain planning
at certain important junctures of your
career is very important because uh it
all depends on your strengths weaknesses
core skills where and how do you want to
land in your career like if you start
your job you might say that okay I like
it I don't like it five years down the
line I want to be here so that way you
need to start a bit of planning as well
and also you need to be very observant
in terms of how industry is shaping so I
wouldn't say that planning is not needed
for sure it is needed but yeah I planned
it when I thought okay now something is
happening that either with me my skill
set or industry or things around me and
that is when I say okay let me plan this
for the next couple of years and then
after this I'll be probably doing this
interesting see mentioned about being
observant about the industry how can one
go about doing that in the present time
like there's so much happening so how
can one do that so I'll give you an
example of how I changed it at couple of
points in my career so I started my
journey as a graphic designer I landed
with a job into e-learning of course it
was learning on job and then that is the
best learning you can seek so after
being a graphic designer I got into
visual designing illustrations and
whatever you may call it so that
creative feeli then um slowly I
understood that by around 2008 now
user experience design was kind of
emerging or entering into India and that
is when I got curious about that what is
ux design I did not have exposure before
that into ux design and I thought okay
it has come from outside and then it's
going to pick up over here so I started
learning about it I started
understanding that what is user
experience design right to my surprise a
lot of uh answers I already had like the
lot of knowledge I already had but I
would say it came into wrapped up in a
different rapper kind of thing so as a
ux design so it is very scientific way
of looking at things um very technical
way of looking at things there is a
different thought process you need to
put across so that's how I picked up I
said fine couple of years down the line
I want to be expert or I want to say two
to four years I want to be called as an
expert so then eventually I also did a
certification from HFI and to be called
because that's also important one is
like nowadays since you asked me the
question nowadays there is information
overload around you there are too many
people teaching about ux UI or in
general design you don't know right and
it's a very sad situation for folks who
really want to learn but they don't know
which is the right source to validate
and people are there to make money out
of it and which is fair but then the
knowledge has to be that strong enough
to be given so there is a lot of
information overload these days uh but
you need to be smart enough to
understand what to pick up and from what
is recognized in today's time back then
there there could be some other things
but now uh let's say like um that is why
you need to be very active on Medias
like LinkedIn because you know what do
people raise eyebrows for like okay you
did certification from here and then so
that is why I said you need to be
observant around you and that is when
you will get cues of okay so I want to
learn today is this is trending this
topic is trending I don't have knowledge
and then there are 10 things out of
which I can do certification so you need
to do a bit of research and then
finalize okay this is this will get me
some weight if I do a research from this
place then it will give me some kind of
weight and it will help me also with the
some credibility in this topic so this
I'm assuming by default that this
process is not that easy as it
sounds it's a lot of ups and downs right
it's a lot of questioning also it's a
lot of uh like you said figuring out for
yourself what works for me what what
doesn't work for me so now that you've
gone through this whole process and I
mean you are going through another
process right now at a different level
right so how does it feel to be leading
a design team to be building a design
team that's a very interesting question
and today's time there is a question out
in the market that does a designer
really need to become a leader is it
like inevitable you you have to cross
that step or is it okay not to become so
I can say that becoming a design leader
is quite a responsible thing and one
must choose very
carefully because the moment you step up
to that position people start looking up
to you and then you have a huge
responsibility to take care of so it's
not just now you're not just thinking
about your own but yeah you're thinking
about the whole team so in my opinion
some designers are very strong
technically and they can perform
excellent being an individual
contributors right and there is no harm
in going that path and becoming stronger
and stronger and getting more knowledge
in that area I understand that being
designers you have to be empathetic
towards everyone around you you need to
know but then everyone has different
background everyone may not be that
extra
or can have or can exercise being a
leader or those tools of leader so
efficiently and effectively so there is
no pressure to be taken here right
because to tell you it's should not be a
step that you must cross being a
designer if you think you are a leader
material then definitely you should
become because there is a need there is
a need for good leaders to be there
because as I said lot of people are
looking up to you but then what does it
feel like being a leader it feels like
you've got an opportunity to enhance few
other lives and you are there to bring
in the change now bringing the change
with other designers or in the design or
become that effective I would say the
facilitator or that element which can
accelerate the process that is why you
should become a leader and that is what
it feels like that you've got an
opportunity to and that is what I have
always cherished it's like it was a
point when I thought like okay it it has
come coming to me naturally that
advising people okay can you do this can
you try to do it this way that way so I
thought okay that's that's how I can
step into it and becoming a leader and
then of course there are few no-brainer
pointers when you want to be a design
leader of course you need to be strong
technically in most of the design
faculty
like I personally believe that even if
you call yourself UI designer you need
to be strong enough to understand the ux
principles ux practices right also user
ux research anywhere I have built a team
or handled a team I have always tried to
give the confidence that you are a
designer be ux or UI you can do all
things under the umbrella of a design
it's just a matter of gaining the
knowledge once you wear cap of a
designer you can do everything so you
need to be technically
strong uh you need to have the sense of
responsibility towards the team in terms
of mentoring leading towards your work
towards your task and a great
maturity right for accessing and
adapting to the environment around you
and keep going on your own path and as
well as taking the team along but this
also comes with a lot of challenges in
how you handle the team in different
situations and in different uh uh let's
say different during different projects
right because everybody's different like
you said and not everybody wants to be a
leader not everybody is wired to be a
leader also so how do you handle the
team when you know that they are tough
situations sometimes where you have to
take the call you have to say no to
people say yes to people then you have
to take them along so how do you do that
as you said it is tough it doesn't mean
that you if you are a leader it will be
very easy for you no that's the
challenging role that it is tough but
then you need to have a one-on-one
connect with every person in the team
and you need to have that equal
relationship no matter the role of that
Designer in the team but you need to
have that one-on-one relationship with
the team uh that Communication channel
should be open both ways you should feel
comfortable able talking to the person
and the other person should feel equally
comfortable talking to you about
anything and everything so if you have
all the paths this transactional paths
very open without any
blockages then that's the first step
that you need to have that conversation
Channel wide open with everyone and to
keep it going there are challenges that
happen personally with designers or as a
team on projects so you need to be
skillful enough to be able to sense it
that something is happening it cannot be
into your own silo or share that okay I
don't know I I don't want to deal with
it no you cannot do that you need to
sense something is happening and then
you need to confront it with that person
I mean could be lunch hours Coffee hours
or any any any time during the reviews
or whatever so that is something you
need to sense it you need to give them
the assurance that okay
be open and I'm there kind of like we
will solve it together so that is the
kind of assurance is something that team
always seeks when they have a leader and
they should feel a comfortable space a
trusted place a place where they get to
grow from their mistakes lot of effort
from both the sides but lot of effort
from the leaders side here to make all
of these adjustment while thinking about
the business and everything as well it's
so during this process while you are
leading the team you've been leading
teams and building teams there's one
thing that I always wanted to ask a
design leader is that so when you are in
a leadership position you it takes you
years of experience to reach there and
it also means that there are people who
are in your team who are much
younger let's say who have just finished
college and joined your team and they
have the let's say whatever Technologies
whatever the trends are there they are
fast faster to adapt or let's say not
faster to adapt I would say they are
more within the circle where those
things are discussed widely and they are
more easy to let's say pick up on things
like this so has it ever happened that a
much younger person in the team has
brought up something that the let's say
the senior designers or those people did
not think of so how does the team handle
that how do you handle that sort of a
situation have you ever faced that sort
of a situation for sure because whatever
teams I have being with always being
younger team okay okay because of my age
I'm not their age but then yeah so this
has happened and as I said you know
every person is important you need to
make sure that every designer is equally
important in your team and you as a
leader need to be be everyone's
cheerleader so be a Junior M designer
who brings in some idea that first thing
you should do in the team is back back
that design around that be his or her
cheerleader like okay yeah I mean it's
great that you've got it why don't you
share it with everyone but do that
consistently with every person in the
team so that brings in the confidence
that every person in the team is
important because of course it's like
it's a multi faed thing every person
shapes the team in a different way
brings in the different perspective
skills into the team so yes definitely
there are situations that happen and
then I typically encourage them in the
standups that we have that why don't you
speak about it like I bring in that
topic if someone is hesitant like you
said such and such thing yesterday it's
a great tool why don't you talk about it
right or if I'm talking to some other
designers who are mid-level senior and
then they are having similar problem and
then I suggest that okay this person has
just discovered something and created
some great stuff why don't you speak and
seek knowledge from this person and then
I connect both of
them and I've seen it works well people
don't take offense over it I think
because if everyone is supported then
this works well so when you have a mix
of people here every company has a way
of operating uh there's a process to it
there's their own way of doing things
and also individuals have their own way
of doing things so what is the process
that you follow with your team if you
have to solve a problem let's say for
digital experiences because that's where
your work mainly is right now so what is
the kind of process that you follow so I
can say this place where I'm working
right now at I Lombard this is um much
complex Place why complex because their
business is much complex and they have
different types of platforms run by
different methods and hence complex so I
would say the process is not like a kind
of a secret recipe that will work with
every organization at every step of
course there are some amendments you
need to do in order to fit that place
and that
ways of working at that b right so first
and foremost thing I feel is important
that wherever you go whichever
organization is understand the maturity
level say when I'm I'm talking about
digital transformation digital Journey
about design so where does your
organization stand in terms of the
design
maturity and then kind of figure out in
your head that this is the gap where you
need to fill in which your team's
presence or with your team being
operational in this organization this is
the gap you need to so you have kind of
set at least the map for yourself that
okay you this organization is at this
level you need to take it to a certain
level and then you start crafting your
plan and then comes the team which is
very
crucial then you need to establish a
proper team structure uh which will fit
well for this plan and uh work well for
all the projects that you are going to
undertake in order to successfully
execute or reach your goal of that
maturity level right you start there
where which is you can say assess the
situation because as a designer a be a
designer then just zoom out there is a
community then there is a country this
is how it goes so every level has a
different level of design maturity right
every designer has a different level of
maturity every Community every country
absolutely every
organization so you need to be to have
that understanding of where you are
standing so assessing your situation
where you are at and then okay this is
where you want to take the organization
now what are the tools your tools are
yourself and your team right your team
is going to take you this organization
to the level X for example now you need
to have a mix of everything in your team
so establishing team structure is
crucial right then I can say of course
uh what comes is setting up Cadence in
terms of communication channels and how
your team will communicate within
themselves how your team will
communicate with Outsiders now Outsiders
could be the product managers Outsiders
could be the tech teams Outsiders could
be the business heads right the
so that is how you kind of set by
examples okay this is our Cadence of how
our team will operate you also set
processes you also set if you have to
get into details of file structures like
how your file structures would be of
course like when I said team onboarding
is also very crucial part of it hiring
and onboarding yeah because that is
something the first gate for any person
to get into the organization so it has
to be done correctly the onboarding and
welcoming of that Designer into the team
is also very important that person
should feel that Designer is in the
right place and you should keep checking
with them as well then again over and
over again you need to be aligned you
need to make sure that your team is
aligned with organization's Vision or
your team's goals so in your weekly team
meeting or your daily standups you can
keep bringing this fact that okay we
know that our goals are 1 two three and
then how are we towards it or whatever
one thing I always keep telling my team
and telling to myself is every
stakeholder is important and that
stakeholder as I said could be anyone
right from designer to pm to business
head to anyone who can give input to
shape up your design every stakeholder
is important but at the same time you
need to put your foood down when it
comes to designing user experience
because you're the expert there because
in such situations in such organization
it always happens like a business head
will say that I have an idea let's do it
this way or a PM will say that I know
this is tried and tested let's do it
this way right but okay then there you
need to educate designer at any level
that you are the gatekeeper for user
experience design you're supposed to
tell them that okay just tell me what
needs to be done and I'll get it done I
would say yeah in an overall these are
the things that how you should follow
and to summarize four things I always
say is like priortize
iterate measure and adapt very well
summarized actually prioritize ideate
isolate measure and adapt so
prioritizing is not very easy and if you
don't have a Clarity seek Clarity always
oh yes very important yeah if you don't
ask a question the answer is always no
so you should always seek Clarity and
that will help you prioritize so you can
add a
sub step to it that seek Clarity and
then start with priortize iterate
measure and adapt I think this puts into
perspective everything all the decisions
that have to be taken very very clearly
sort of like a road map this forward
approach let's say very cool so also I'm
want to ask you about the team here now
now we've been talking about teams and
you know building the team so once
you've hired people we'll come to the
hiring part a little bit later in the
conversation but once you've hired the
team it's important to sustain the team
so all these things that you've
mentioned one-on-one relationship and
giving them the opportunity to speak
giving them the opportunity to let's say
Network or gain some exposure all of
those things considering that those
things are there in an
organization or in a team right now so
what other practices as part of your
journey have you tried and tested that
work to sustain the team as you said
definitely that is there for sustaining
a team you feel that you as a person you
feel you belong to a place if you are
given a task that is challenging that
will let you exercise your expertise
that that place will make you feel that
you are trusted that will give you a
confidence that will give you some perks
in a way people feel talk good about you
about your achievement you are being
valued so that is a place where people
feel okay I belong here I'm good here
that is the kind of environment you need
to set up and of course set it by
example then again people are hungry
about learning new things and that is
why you need to have the place where
there is abundance of knowledge and
there is exchange of material that
happens frequently and you should
encourage the team also to do so and
that is how you can step in and say that
okay found this material this could be
useful understand the gaps that any
individually people are feeling and or
as a collectively as a team and keep
sourcing latest trends or the new
material or knowledge which is which is
in this field that helps other things
could be that keep transparency as I
mentioned earlier with one on once keep
transparency with the team let them
never be in the dark beat anything you
should be the one who should tell them
any different decision information that
is happening they should not hear it
from anywhere else so that is how they
can feel trusted also build a strong
Network for leveraging know knowledge
support and sustainance I would say
within the team you share knowledge you
ask them to share knowledge but also
build a community in your organization
where they get a chance to share
something from their own so they feel
that okay I'm contributing as a part of
a design Community I think this touches
on every aspect of that makes it let's
say make the people want to belong the
sense of belonging that we talked about
I think it is actually touching on every
aspect of it it's quite interesting
and is it easy to do all of that I think
if you always practice it yeah first
time it will be like okay you need to
keep remembering okay am I doing good I
should do 1 2 3 4 but it's not difficult
I would say because these are the things
which motivate you to do your work
effectively efficiently and why not if
you're introducing new tools that will
help you say synthesize the data faster
with with there are so many it to these
days for research for whatever usability
testing that you've done then sharing
that knowledge is going to help the team
the team is going to feel that oh I I I
can now do it better so these tools are
going to empower the team even more so I
mean this again requires a lot of effort
from the leadership side and also from
the senior designers Etc so when you're
putting in so much effort to make the
team comfortable and sustainable
practices and all of those things I'm
sure you're very particular about who
you bring to the team so let's talk
about that a little bit so what is it
that you look at now this is a very
general or generic question but I think
every every leader every team has its
own requirements and the company has its
own requirements so I would like to know
you having worked at different companies
and led different teams and built
different teams what are the core things
that you look at irrespective of the
company that you know people might want
to apply at yes definitely there are
things that you have to look at the
company and include projects or you know
let's say customize whatever I'm sending
to the company but what are the core
things that should be there as a
designer in my experience what I have
understood is see there are two things
one is your vision or expectation of
someone who's going to get on Bard H
that this is the kind of person I want
which is mostly aligned with the
organizations or your team's
requirements so you go in with that
perspective when you conduct interviews
the designer outside designer doesn't
know anything what is happening inside
your organization what is apart from the
job role that is given apart from how
the situation how the organization or
the team is what is the actual
expectation has no idea about it so he
or she is totally alien into what you
have in your head so at the very first
interview level I feel it is very
important to get that on the same page
give the perspective of see this is what
is happening here and this is what is
expected and if you think you're the
great fot because if you want it to work
from both the ends the worst thing that
happens and it has definitely happened
quite a lot of times also that may not
be the best in taking the decision of
hiring someone yeah there are some
mistakes happen but I would say the
mistake is because of the expectation
mismatch that's all you need to align
those expectation and because of the
expectation mismatch that doesn't mean
that person is not good but probably
that person would have fitted in some
other organization or in some other
situation or other requirement but not
here yeah so every situation or team
requirement organization requirement
demands you to carefully craft and
understand this is the type of of a
designer I would need at this point in
time let's say after 6 months it might
need to go alterations so that is
something you should have a Clarity in
your head that what is the need of an
hour who do I need okay I have someone
let's say there is nothing good or bad
but let's say I have couple of designer
who are very SP soft spoken but that has
not worked in this situation I need
someone who is very aggressive and I
need someone who will drive it I mean
the softspoken designers it works very
well when they design but then they get
intimidated by the other stakeholders
the work doesn't get done so I need some
leader who will understand their
strengths and lead the team and get the
work done right so that is one example I
gave you what I look for understanding
the right need of requirement at that
point in time but what I look into as a
designer is attitude the very first
important thing is at attitude you
cannot mock it you cannot take it I mean
you you need to have a good attitude
that's all it works wonders of course
next comes is technical skills you
should have a drive to be better and I
always personally feel someone who is up
for challenges is always keeps on going
learning new things right and of course
a can do proven attitude of can do that
also helps so this has a lot to do with
the kind of personality or the character
that we buil and then comes the work
side of it the technical knowhow I think
those things can be taught is what I'm
assuming is that how you those things
can be taught but yeah I would say the
tech technical skills is equally
important of course like you don't have
always a liberty to on board the person
and also give that person two to three
months to learn everything yeah today's
time don't afford can't afford to do
that so we need someone expert to be hon
board very important things have been
discussed in a very simple way in this
episode I'm sure if all all the things
that You' have mentioned if people all
the listeners specifically the people
who are applying or you know want to
grow up the ladder if they take each and
every one of it and follow it I think
that can do wonders for sure and one
last thing that I would like to ask you
is when the person gets hired and we've
just talked about the softs spoken
designers or designers who get
intimidated by the other stakeholders or
voice their not opinions or their
designs or Justify their designs so how
to safeguard that individuality while
working within a team how can one do
that so one is again talk to that
Designer give them a confidence that
it's not bad to feel intimidated but you
also need to put your point across
effectively sometimes it helps if you
pair a team member who talks more
confidently or is not afraid to put
their point of view across so a
softspoken designer May learn from the
co-designer or also have them lead which
could be like tag them with you being a
lead that see or push them into
situations and Shadow them help them how
they should now communicate what they
should say how they should react respond
so handhold them into certain situations
that will show them the way when they
see the results they will understand
that okay yeah this way of working works
and before we close the episode for
today and the conversation I would like
to ask if there if are there any
openings at your team that you're
looking for where can people apply where
can people reach out to you there are
opening there are at least a couple of
openings in my team and then they can
reach out to me on LinkedIn that will be
easiest or HR who's on LinkedIn
typically in few of my post I have
tagged them all right so they can either
approach them or approach me on LinkedIn
any dos and don'ts with their portfolios
or the way they approach that's okay you
can guess what you want to get from the
approach so I wouldn't want to say the
dos and don'ts uh but yeah um portfolio
yeah you need not be very generic
portfolio you can bring in the skill if
you are able to show your skill in a
good way yeah perfect thank you so much
analii and this was a lovely
conversation I hope you also enjoyed it
as much as I did yeah it was my pleasure
Sanjay I mean you yourself are doing a
doing some great things in design field
thank you yeah